All
right, so today's דף daf. *Daf* will be צדי ח׳ *Tzadi Chet*
98, but just to summarize what we did yesterday because it was
a very major concept. We saw a first משנה Mishnah *Mishna* that
discussed the איסור issur. *Issur* of גיד הנשה *Gid Hanashe* with the
אשישי *Ashishai*. The basic theme that came out of that משנה Mishna.
*Mishna* was that when כשר kosher *Kosher* and non-כשר kosher *Kosher* soak
with כשר kosher *Kosher*, you have to determine whether or not taste
was imparted. And if taste was imparted, obviously you can't eat it.
That's the principle called טעם כעיקר Ta'am ke-ikar *Ta'am Ke'ikar*, taste is
like the thing itself, which is debated in another גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
whether it's biblical or not. But the general assumption is that it
is biblical and that it might even be considered like the original
איסור issur *Issur*. So that's the issue about giving taste. The next
part of the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* spoke about if you can't identify
the original object, which we'll get to later in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So then in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* itself, we had a
couple of interesting things. First of all, it was questions about what
transfers taste. Our משנה Mishnah *Mishna* mentioned cooking. So שמואל *Shmuel* mentioned
three other things. One was roasting, which שמואל *Shmuel*
says transfers to the... doesn't transfer at all is the literal meaning
of שמואל *Shmuel*, that if you roast the גיד *Gid* it doesn't
do anything. But תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* and other ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* say
that no, you actually do transfer to the like a thin layer
immediately next to the thing roasted. But it certainly doesn't spread throughout
the whole thing, unless of course what you're roasting is fatty, and
then it becomes practical questions about can we discern between what is
and not fatty. The other way of transferring is not with heat
but with salting and pickling, which also was a statement of שמואל
*Shmuel*. And שמואל *Shmuel* says salting is like direct heat, which means
like roasting, so it transfers very little but it does transfer somewhat,
according to the conventional understanding.
And pickling because of the presence of liquid, שמואל *Shmuel* says is
like cooking and transfers things that are pickled together transfers throughout. So
that's one question about how do you transfer taste, normally with heat
but there are these other things which are seen as substitutes of
heat. The other important principles that we raised yesterday, and which are
going to of course be our focus, is how do you... is
when things are cooked together, how do you determine whether or not
it's a problem, whether it imparted taste. So our משנה *Mishna* mentioned
taste, and it mentioned like what do you do if you can't
taste it because it's not כשר kosher *Kosher*, and it mentioned ways
of creating some type of a model of taste. You imagine as
if the גיד *Gid* was meat and as if the rest of
the thing were turnips. So one approach is to try to focus
on really trying to get to taste it to get some model
or to get some way of measuring taste if you can't taste
it. And there was another statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi
Yochanan* that you used onions to be a stand-in for the איסור
issur *Issur*. So you would determine whether or not taste would transfer
had the forbidden thing, which obviously you're not allowed to taste and
sometimes you don't even know what the taste is, had the forbidden
thing been an onion and been cooked in the pot, would the
taste spread? Which obviously is a stringency because onions are going to
be more stringent than most things. But anyway, that's one model, which
is the model of the משנה *Mishna* of taste. Then there's another
model which רש״י Rashi, *Rashi* is very clear from the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* but רש״י Rashi *Rashi* actually spells it out very quickly, is
the model of using sixty, using a quantitative measure. If there's sixty
times as much it's not a problem, if there's less than sixty
times as much then it is a problem. And that's a stand-in
for determining
whether or not taste will be imparted. So there really are those
two models, if something איסור issur *Issur* is cooked with היתר heter,
*Heter*, it's a problem if there's taste. And the question is how
do you determine taste? Either you make some type of a model
of a stand-in like onions and you do some experiment or something,
or you use a simple quantifiable rule of sixty, but that's going
to be strict because that's going to be trying to sort of
be the same and therefore
cover all cases. So those are really the two models that we
were presented with and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually said the
important thing was the statement of
רב *Rav* because... excuse me, not רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, רב *Rav*.
It was רב *Rav* that there are... but first רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* said that if you can't taste you can get a non-Jew
to taste. Right. So that was surprising that you can rely on
a non-Jew and there's a discussion in later פוסקים *Poskim* under what
circumstances? Only if their reputation is at stake or only if they
don't know you're relying on them and so on. But you can
rely on a non-Jew to taste it. Excuse me, I don't know
what that is.
I'm sorry, hold on. Okay.
Anyway, and you can rely on a non-Jew. And then רבא Rava
*Rava*, I think it's רבא *Rava*, says that there really you can
bring these models together and you can say that if it's something
that is כשר kosher *Kosher*,
then you can... then... I'm
sorry, if it's something that's כשר kosher *Kosher*... something's
very upset. If it's something that is כשר kosher then you can
take, go by the taste of a Jew. A Jew can taste
it. If it's something non-כשר kosher then you could use a non-Jew
to taste it. If however it's something that you can't find a
non-Jew to taste it or there's things that are cooked together and
there's no way to determine the taste then you use the model
of שישים. shishim. So there's a case where actually he brings all
those different models together, the taste model and the שישים shishim model,
and says that different ones will work under different circumstances. Okay, and
as the last thing we said, and this is the end of
the summary, is that how do we rule? So ספרדים Sephardim actually
rule like the simple approach in the גמרא Gemara which is that
they actually will go by taste, the taste of a Jew for
היתר, heter the taste of a non-Jew for איסור. issur אשכנזים Ashkenazim
however go really pretty much—don't like things that are more contextual and
so on and they really don't go by taste and they always
demand שישים shishim although in principle they would rely on the taste
of a Jew if it were necessary. But as a basic rule
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim only go by שישים. shishim. Yes.
So a question is, given we said taste, how does the onion
fit into that?
I
mean, is that only—onion? The onion. Onion. What do you mean? Oh,
because if you don't have—that was assuming that you didn't have a
non-Jew around but you wanted to try to do your own experiment.
So therefore it was the onion. That was the onion thing, but
the onion model quickly got replaced once it was introduced by רבי
יוחנן that you use a non-Jew which is not in any of
the תנאי Tannaitic sources, right, then the need for something like that
type of an onion model or the model in the משנה became
less so.
Right, so we don't actually do anything. So the onion has no
practical ramification.
Right, mostly since we basically have ruled that you go by—what do
you call it? That you can use a non-Jew, there's really no
need to do something like that onion model. Okay. All right, so
now let's start the דף. daf All right, so we had just
summarized yesterday's דף daf which had the basic principles about taste and
שישים shishim and now we pick up on the bottom—today's דף daf.
again is צדיק ח, tzadik chet, 98. We pick up on the
bottom of צדיק ז עמוד ב, tzadik zayin amud bet, three lines,
four lines from the bottom. ביעה בשישים ואין ביעה מן המנין. Beita
beshishim vein beita min haminyan. If you have an egg then the
egg goes by 60. But, you know, if you have a non-כשר
kosher egg you need 60 times it. But and you don't count
the egg as one of the 60, which is obvious because the
normal rule is you need 60 against the thing that's אסור. assur.
So אמר ליה רב אידי בר אבין לאביי. amar lei Rava Idi
bar Abin l'Abaye. So רב אידי בר אבין Rava Idi bar Abin
says to אביי: Abaye: למימרא lemeimra this suggests דיהיבא טעמא d'yahiva ta'ama
that if you cook an egg with other eggs taste will impart.
But that's not so clear. First of all there's hard shells to
block the taste and how much taste comes out of an egg
anyway? והא אמרי אינשי v'ha amri inshi
don't people say כמיא דביעי בעלמא? k'maya d'bei'ei b'alma? You know, this
thing is like totally bland, it's like egg water. So that's a
way of expressing something that gave no taste into something is the
water from cooking eggs. So it's an interesting—they use that as an
example, but obviously they're not just proving it from the expression, but
the expression reflects reality. So why are you concerned about cooking a
non-כשר kosher egg with other eggs? אמר ליה amar lei so he
said הכא במאי עסקינן hacha b'mai askinan what are we talking about?
בביצת אפרוח bebeitat efro'ach
that it's not an egg on top of צדיק ח עמוד
א.
tzadik
chet amud aleph.
What—what is a non-כשר kosher egg?
A non-כשר kosher egg would be an egg from a non-כשר kosher
bird,
let's say an egg from an ostrich.
Oh, not from a chicken.
Yeah, yeah, no, an ostrich egg. Or it could be an egg
from a טרפה, treif, let's say a chicken was a טרפה treif
and it had an egg. Assuming that a טרפה treif could lay
eggs. Okay, so anyway the answer is though that it's not כשר
kosher. because it's got a chicken inside. If it's got a chicken
inside then it's not so bland, then it has the—and a chicken—and
an egg, an unhatched egg, even from a כשר kosher animal is
considered like a נבלה. neveilah. It's like there's a live animal that
hasn't been שחט. shochted. So that's a real problem and therefore that
gives off the taste into the other eggs. אבל טמאה לא aval
t'meiah lo but if it's just from a non-כשר kosher animal that
would not be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says איתיבי eitvei
I'll ask you on that: ביצים תערובת ששלקן עם ביצים טמאות. beitzim
tarovet sheshalkun im beitzim t'meiot. If you have כשר kosher. eggs which
you boiled together with non-כשר kosher eggs, again meaning from כשר kosher
and non-כשר kosher animals, אם יש בהם נותן טעם כולן אסורות. im
yesh bahem noten ta'am kulan asurot. If it gives taste it's a
problem. So you see we're assuming it could theoretically give taste even
though it's a case of non-כשר. kosher So the גמרא Gemara says
הכא נמי בביצת אפרוח hacha nami bebeitat efro'ach and when it says
non-כשר it doesn't mean from a non-כשר bird, it means from a—that
there's a chicken inside. Okay, that's what it means non-כשר. ואמאי קרי
ליה טמאה umai kari lei t'meiah why does it call it non-כשר
which normally would mean non-כשר species?
כיון דאית בה אפרוח קרי ליה טמאה keivan d'it ba efro'ach kari
lei t'meiah because it's not כשר because it's got a chicken inside,
but it's not really the problem that it comes from a non-כשר
bird, it's a problem that it has a chicken inside and that's
the only time you're concerned about the egg giving off taste.
But an egg—you can see a difference between a chicken
egg—right, so somebody wasn't paying attention you know, or it was being
cooked in some industrial setting and then you know you're at a
hotel and they served you hard-boiled eggs for breakfast and they laid
out all
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says והא מדקתני סיפא ביצים ששלקן
ונמצא אפרוח באחת מהן *ve'ha midektani
seifa beitzim sheshalkon venimtza efroach be'achat mehen*. If you boiled eggs and
you found a chick in one of them, אם
יש בהן בנותן טעם ta'am כולן אסורות *im yesh bahen benoten ta'am
kulan asurot*,
if it gave off taste it's forbidden. So that gave it a
separate case. מכלל דרישא *mikhlal deresha* that infers that the first case
where it didn't mention a chick, it just mentioned non-kosher, דלאו באפרוח
עסקינן *delav be'efroach askinan*,
it's not a case of a chick, it's a case of an
egg from a non-kosher animal and you see even that we're afraid
that it gave off taste. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פירושי
קמפרש *peirushei kamifaresh*. No, no, it's just explaining itself. ביצים טהורות ששלקן
עם ביצים טמאות אם יש בהן בנותן טעם ta'am, כולן אסורות *beitzim
tehorot sheshalkon im beitzim tmeot im yesh bahen benoten ta'am kulan asurot*.
The first line says if you cooked it with a non-kosher egg,
if it gives off taste it's a problem, and then the next
line is clarifying the first line. כיצד *keitzad*? What would be a
case of a non-kosher egg? כגון ששלקן ונמצא אפרוח באחת מהן *kegon
sheshalkon venimtza efroach be'achat mehen*. Like you cooked it and there was
a chick. So although it's written as two cases, it really is
one is explaining the other, exactly, and it really is just the
case of a chick. But if it's a non-kosher egg it doesn't
give off taste.
What, are we saying this was a מין במינו min bemino.
*min bemino* or מין בשאינו מינו *min beshe'eino mino*? Well, the first
case was מין במינו Min be-mino. *min bemino*. Yeah, all eggs was
מין במינו Min be-mino, *min bemino*. I mean, you mean is an
egg of a non-kosher animal considered מין במינו min b'mino *min bemino*
with a kosher animal? I don't know whether the tastes are the
same. The general rule is that it does not go by what
they're called, although this is debated by אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava*
in עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah*, but bracketing that, that's a special case.
The basic rule is it goes by do they have the same
taste or not same taste. So you'd have to ask somebody who's
eaten non-kosher eggs if they have a similar taste or not.
Right, so let's assume that they have a somewhat similar
taste,
okay?
Right. How similar is similar enough? I guess the question is, is
it dissimilar enough that it could be, it's possible to
distinguish? But you're questioning, let's say it's possible to distinguish, but only
if it's very even, only if as soon as the amount gets
to so much as proportionate, it's a good question. It's a good
question. In the end of the day, if you don't know, you
know, you use the sixty measure, ביטול bitul בששים *bitul beshishim*, which
is what we're talking about here, so somewhat of a moot question.
But it is a good point.
Yes, and the one in sixty is in all cases
of נותן טעם ta'am, *noten ta'am*. Right, meaning the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
before said אם יש
בו בנותן טעם Tam
*im yesh bo benoten ta'am*. Exactly. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before said
if you can't determine the taste because it's a
non-Jew or because it tastes the same, you use one in sixty.
So one in sixty becomes the fallback what you use all the
time for same taste, and then the fallback for different tastes when
you're not certain about being able to discern it. So certainly here,
I mean so for most intents and purposes, especially for the אשכנזים
Ashkenazim *Ashkenazim* that never go by really tasting, sixty is always the
rule. There's very little difference except for the question of whether it's
a דאורייתא de-oraita. *de'oraita* or דרבנן drabbanan *derabanan* problem because we assume
that if it's different tastes then it really could impart taste, then
it's a דאורייתא *de'oraita* concern of טרייף *treif* giving off taste. If
it's all the same taste and there is no taste that's going
to be imparted, then the need to have it, that it doesn't
even have the potential to give taste, the whole problem of מין
במינו *min bemino* is only a rabbinic problem, right? Why didn't somebody
say to me, "Hey, why is there a problem if they all
taste the same? Why do you need sixty at all? What do
you mean?
It's the substitute, you shouldn't need anything, it all tastes the same."
That's דרבנן drabbanan. *derabanan* as an extension of when they have different
tastes. So the real difference for אשכנזים *Ashkenazim* between whether it's the
same or different is not how you determine it because אשכנזים *Ashkenazim*
will always go by sixty, the real difference is whether it's a
דאורייתא *de'oraita* concern or not. Yes, Charlie.
They're ignoring this idea that eggs in water aren't absorbing anything, so
this would seem to imply that we couldn't eat a hard-boiled egg
in a non-kosher restaurant.
No, actually from the pot you mean.
Yeah. So that's a good point, meaning there's two questions about why
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is saying that eggs shouldn't be a problem.
One is they don't give off any taste into the water, and
maybe the hard shell prevents them from absorbing taste. The גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* by saying that it matters what is the source of the
problem, if the problem is a chick, then the other eggs are
problematic, will actually say that the shell does not prevent them from
absorbing taste. That is actually correct, although the question still could be
raised, what if the taste is only coming via the water and
the pot and it's not like something directly there and so on?
But that's a good question. So the question about what's the story
with eggs cooked in a non-kosher pot and does the shell prevent
even absorbing taste is actually discussed. But this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does
seem to say that it's not about not absorbing, it's about not
giving off taste. You are completely correct about that. No הלכה Halakha
*halacha* today.
I will get back to you about that. I know you raised
it last time. I should have come today prepared with an answer.
I understand. All right, I understand. But what Charlie is saying is
correct, is that this גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* does assume that if there's
a leniency by eggs, it's that they don't give off taste, not
that they don't absorb taste. Okay, let's keep on going in the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. Okay, הכא נמי מסתברא *hacha nami mistabra*, that makes
sense to assume that it's all one case, דאי סלקא דעתך רישא
דלאו באפרוח *de'i salka daitach resha delav be'efroach*. The first case was
talking about a non-kosher egg which was not talking about a chick.
So השתא לית ביה אפרוח אסורה, if you're going to tell me
it's a problem even if it's no chick that just a non-kosher
egg could give off taste, דאיכא ביה אפרוח מיבעיא, de'is bei afrochos
mibaya, why would you have to tell me the case of a
chick? Obviously that'll give off taste. So someone says no, אי משום
הא לא איריא, ee mishum ha lo irya, if that was your
whole point, that's not, that wouldn't prove it. That's not, you know
why? תנא סיפא לגלויי רישא, Tanna seifa leigluyei reishah, it would tell
you the second case to make it clear what the first case
is. שלא תאמר רישא דאית ביה אפרוח, shello tomar reishah d'is bei
afrochos, which is, you know, probably a more reasonable read of the
ברייתא, Baraita, you shouldn't say that the first case just says not
kosher maybe that means a chick. No, no, no, it's going to
tell you a second case of a chick so you understand that
the first case is talking without a chick and just from a
non-kosher bird. So וממילא u-mimila אבל לית ביה אפרוח שריא, aval lies
bei afrochos sharya,
you might have thought that without a chick it would be completely
permissible for the reasons we even saying. So תנא סיפא דאית ביה
אפרוח, Tanna seifa d'is bei afrochos, it taught a second case of
a case with a chick, מכלל דרישא דלית ביה אפרוח, miklal de-reishah
de-lies bei afrochos, to let you know that the first case of
not kosher meant from a non-kosher bird did not mean a chick,
ואפילו הכי אסורה, v'afillu hachi assurah, and even so it was forbidden,
which is of course the more reasonable read of the ברייתא. Baraita.
The ברייתא Baraita has two cases, presumably they're not all the same
case, right? So what?
Didn't we just explain it that it was?
Yes, but the גמרא Gemara is saying why I could have read,
why it's reasonable to read it the other way, right? The גמרא
Gemara is saying obviously it's the same case, or else why would
you need to even tell me the chick, just tell me the
first case? No, no, no, because it's telling you the chick in
order to tell you a reasonable read of the ברייתא Baraita is
two cases, and it told you the chick so that it's clear
that the other case is not a chick, it's just from a
non-kosher bird and even so it's a problem and it does give
off taste. That's probably the more reasonable read of the ברייתא, Baraita,
but it's interesting here the גמרא Gemara takes a position based on
its sort of real-world knowledge that, you know, normal eggs without chicks
don't give off taste, and actually therefore is willing to say that,
you know, to read the ברייתא Baraita otherwise and to say that
if it's just non-kosher eggs cooked with kosher eggs we're not concerned
about them imparting any taste. So you see there is some degree
of a sort of real-world orientation and that does go back to
the whole discussion about ששים shishim as a stand-in for taste, but
sometimes, you know, we go back to that reality of taste. Okay,
so that's in terms of eggs that if it doesn't have a
chick we're actually not concerned that it gives off taste. But Charlie's
question is appropriate whether we are, we'd assume that it absorbs taste
or not. It does seem that we do assume that it does
absorb. Now we're going to go with a couple of other ways
of determining A, how to measure 60,
and whether we actually go by 60. So let's take a look.
ההיא כזיתא תרבא, Hahi k'zayta tarba, a כזית k'zayit of fat, forbidden
fat, דנפל בדיקולא דבישרא, de-nafal be-dikulah de-bisra, fell into this again, this
pot, like, you know, a stew pot, a boiling pot of meat.
There's a question what דיקולא dikulah means, but that's what רש"י Rashi
says. Okay.
סבר רב אסי Savar Rav Assi or רב אשי Rav Ashi לשעורי
במה דבלע דיקולא. l'shiurei be-mah de-bala dikulah.
He said let's assess it based on what the pot absorbed. This
was an issue that came up yesterday. What does that exactly mean
what the pot absorbed? But רש"י Rashi here says like he described
the case yesterday. Again, not necessarily the only way to read this,
that it came in front of רב אסי Rav Assi like an
hour after it had been cooked and he said oh, so even
though we don't have ששים shishim based on what I'm seeing now,
obviously there was more in the pot that got absorbed over the
last hour, and that will be enough to negate the כזית k'zayit
that fell in if you add what got absorbed into the pot
over the last hour. So that's what he wanted to do and
he wanted to be lenient. So אמרו ליה רבנן לרב אשי, Amru
lei rabbanan le-Rav Ashi, so the rabbis said to רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, אטו דהיתירא בלע דאיסורא לא בלע? atu de-heteira bala d'issura lo
bala? What,
what do you think? It only absorbed from the kosher part of
the stew? It also absorbed from the non-kosher. So even though now
you're seeing less kosher stuff than was there an hour ago when
it fell in, you're also seeing less fat that was there an
hour ago when it fell in, and we'll assume that the pot
absorbed proportionally, and the basic rule therefore is don't worry about what
happened when it fell in originally, you can't really know, look at
what you have right now, look at the proportions right now, and
based on the proportions right now you'll assume it's similar or the
same as the proportions when it happened originally and that will be
your basis for determining ששים shishim or not. Okay, so this based
on this גמרא Gemara with how רש"י Rashi interpreted yesterday's גמרא Gemara
about what the pot absorbed, although there are possible ways of reading
yesterday's גמרא. Gemara Okay, now we're going to the question about whether
you use 60 or some other measure. ההוא פלגא דזיתא, Hahu palga
d'zayta, this,
there was a half of a כזית, k'zayit, ההוא פלגא
דזיתא דתרבא, hahu palga d'zayta d'tarba, half of a כזית k'zayit of
fat. So if it's only half כזית k'zayit you wouldn't get lashes
even if you ate it. דנפל בדיקולא דבישרא, de-nafal be-dikulah de-bisra, fell
into this again, this pot of meat. סבר מר בר רב אשי
לשעורי בתלתין. Savar Mar bar Rav Ashi l'shiurei b'tlasin. So מר בר
רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi said, oh, בתלתין פלגי דזיתא. b'tlasin
palgei d'zayta. It's enough to have 30 against it. Now and you
shouldn't be confused it means 30 זיתים zaysin which is 60 times,
no, no, no, 30 halves. A half-זית *zayit* fell in, it's enough
to have thirty half-זיתין *zaitin*. He didn't need sixty, he only needed
thirty. Okay, which is interesting. And we're going to see in a
minute that basically he wanted to be
lenient because if it was only half of a כזית *kezayit* it
wasn't enough to get lashes on, so maybe since it was only,
he thought, a rabbinic problem, we could be more lenient in terms
of what is the שיעור *shiur* that we require.
Would it work proportionally?
That's not clear. אמר ליה amar leih, אבוה *Amar lei avuh*, so
his father רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, who was in the previous גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that I just, the previous line one second, and wanted
to be lenient and got pushed back from his students, so רב
אשי *Rav Ashi* said to him, so לאו אמינא לך *lav amina
lach*, haven't I told you לא תזלזל בשיעורין דרבנן *lo tizalzel b'shiurin
d'rabbanan*? Do not be lenient with rabbinic שיעורין *shiurin*. Now, what does
דרבנן *d'rabbanan* there modify? It seems based on context it modifies the
fact, a שיעור *shiur* on a rabbinic prohibition. Although this is only
rabbinically prohibited because it's only half a כזית *kezayit*, don't be lenient.
But it could modify that the שיעור *shiur* is rabbinic. That really
biblically the שיעור *shiur* is, first of all there's a question if
טעם ta'am *taam* itself is biblical, but let's assume it is, which
is, you know, the overwhelming consensus. But the whole use of sixty
is a rabbinic stand-in and is a like a worst-case scenario. So
maybe since the whole sixty is a worst-case scenario, maybe sometimes we
can fudge it a little bit and go by thirty under certain
circumstances. So he says, no, don't be lenient. Don't be lenient even
though the prohibition is rabbinic, don't be lenient even maybe if the
number sixty is only a rabbinic stand-in and it's only a worst-case
scenario. ועוד *v'od*, one minute, and more than that, דאורייתא בי טעם
ta'am *d'Oraita bi taam*, the taste isn't always sixty, very often it's
less than sixty. Sixty is a worst-case scenario. ועוד *v'od*, and in
addition, who says this is rabbinic? אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*,
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says חצי שיעור אסור מן התורה *chatzi shiur
asur min haTorah*, that even if it's not the full amount it's
biblically prohibited. You don't get lashes, but it's still biblically prohibited. So
this is anyway a biblical prohibition. Okay.
ומי אית ליה איסור
כרת *V'mi it lei issur kares*? No. You don't get the punishment
for eating less than a כזית *kezayit*. You, it's a חצי שיעור
*chatzi shiur* of an איסור כרת *issur kares*. Okay, so that's an
interesting question. Is a half of a שיעור *shiur* of an איסור
כרת *issur kares* more severe than a half of a שיעור *shiur*
of an איסור לאו *issur lav*? That's a question the רמב"ן *Ramban*
raises. And if we were learning this סוגיא Sugya *sugya* in יומא
*Yoma*, I would tell you more about that. But anyway, it is
biblical. אמר רב שמעון בר אבא Abba, אמר רב אידי בר אידי
*Amar Rav Shimon bar Abba amar Rav Idi bar Idi*, בר אידי
*bar Idi*, interesting, בר גרשום *bar Gershom*, אמר לוי בר פרטא אמר
רב נחמן אמר רב בירם *amar Levi bar Parta amar Rav Nachman
amar Rav Biram*, wow, long tradition there, a lot of people whose
names are not so familiar, משום זקן אחד *mishum zaken echad*, in
the name of a certain elder, רבי יעקב שמו *Rabbi Yaakov shemo*,
דבי נשיאה אמרו *d'vei nesi'ah amru*, and they said in the house
of the נשיא *nasi*, so this is post-רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הנשיא
*Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi* but from his family, ביצה בששים אסורה *beitzah b'shishim
asurah*, בששים ואחת מותרת *b'shishim v'achat muteres*, which seems to be like
we said before. We're not so clear though. If there's sixty it's
forbidden, sixty-one it's permissible. So are you counting sixty other than the
egg itself? And then it's interesting, then we're saying that it's not
enough to have sixty, you need sixty-one, we're being more strict by
an egg, which is quite strange. So let's take a look. אמר
רב זירא לרב שמעון בר אבא *Amar Rav Zeira l'Rav Shimon bar
Abba*, so רב זירא *Rav Zeira* said to רב שמעון בר אבא
*Rav Shimon bar Abba*, ראה שאתה מטיל בה גבול היתר heter *re'eh
she'atah matil bah gevul heter*, look that you are drawing a line
when it becomes permissible. By saying sixty-one and sixty, you're making, you're
saying okay there's a stage where it's permissible. Well obviously, but the
point is once you're saying when it's permissible, you need to be
a little bit clearer. Why is he not clear? שהרי שני גדולי
הדור לא פירשו את הדבר *Sheharei shnei gedolei hador lo pirshu es
hadavar*. There were two great people of the generation that they were
not, they did not explain this fully. And that's a problem. Who
was it? What was the case? רבי יעקב בר אידי ורבי שמואל
בר נחמני *Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi v'Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani*, those, רבי
יעקב *Rabbi Yaakov* and רבי שמואל *Rabbi Shmuel*, דתרוייהו משמיה דרבי יהושע
בן לוי אמרי *d'traivaihu mishmeih d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amri*, they both
said in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, ביצה בששים אסורה *beitzah b'shishim asurah*, בששים
ואחת מותרת *b'shishim v'achat muteres*, that with sixty it's forbidden, sixty-one it's
permissible. Okay, which is just like what you said. But they actually,
that was their tradition, but they actually had doubts what it meant.
What are the ways of interpreting it? ואיבעיא להו *V'ibaia lehu*, they
raised the question, בששים ואחת בהדי הדדי *b'shishim v'achat bahadi hadadi*, בהדי
דידי *bahadi didi*, when we say sixty-one is permissible, sixty-one including it,
so there's a total of sixty-one eggs, which is the normal ruling.
You have the forbidden thing and sixty additional opposite it. So that
would be the normal thing to say, sixty-one is permissible including the
thing itself, you have a total of sixty-one eggs. או דילמא *O
dilma*, or do we say that for some reason being even more
strict by an egg, דילמא לבר מיניה *dilma l'var mineih*, outside of
the thing itself, that we're even, that we're saying that you need
it plus another sixty-one against it, which is very bizarre. Normally you
only need sixty. ולא פשיט *V'lo pashit*, and they didn't know what
their, you know, how to explain their tradition. Is it enough to
have sixty against it or do you need sixty-one against it? ומר
פשיט ליה מיפשט *U'mar pashit lei mifshat*, and you're just teaching it
straight without clarifying. That's not helpful. Since this key tradition is one
that's a little ambiguous, you have a responsibility to clarify right what
do you mean? Do you mean sixty other than the original egg
or including the egg itself? Okay, so that was just a little
bit of pushback, but what's interesting is a bizarre idea that although
before we had one exception to the opposite, that with כחחל *k'chachal*
you only needed fifty-nine opposite, here we're having a possibility that by
an egg you have a little exception to be more strict, that
you need not sixty opposite but sixty-one opposite. and no real reason
is given. So the ראשונים rishonim, try to give different reasons, I
forgot to check what the reasons are but somehow that because it's
maybe significant and it's a separate thing, although a lot of things
are significant and separate and we only need, we only need sixty.
So I don't even remember the reason the ראשונים give why you
might need, why you might be more strict here by the egg.
It is a little bit strange given of course exactly what we
said before,
that what do you call it, that egg is it might give
off even less taste, you know, even almost no taste. Okay, but
here's the possibility maybe that's why we're a little bit more strict
is you might come to be lenient by eggs. Okay, so that's
that, that the eggs there's a possibility you need not sixty but
sixty-one. Okay, now back to the whole question of sixty. ההוא, Hahu,
so remember we saw before of somebody that in one case מר
בר אשי Mar bar Ashi wanted to do thirty, right? Sixty is
not in any משנה.
What?
אתמר. Itmar.
No, up to ההוא דאתא. Hahu de-ata. We're up to אתמר. Itmar.
Oh, you're right. אתמר. Itmar. אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה Amar
Rav Yitzchak bereih de-Rav Yehuda ביצה בשישים ומה היא אסורה Beitza beshishim
u-mah hi asura בשישים ואחת והיא מותרת. Beshishim ve-achat ve-hi muteret. So
sixty including it, I'm sorry, well that's also a question
about how you read it. So רש"י Rashi reads it בשישים beshishim
plus it
it is forbidden, sixty-one, I'm sorry sixty-one plus it for a total
of sixty-two it's permissible. So that we actually are more strict by
eggs and that we say that an egg you need not sixty
against it but sixty-one against it. Why is a little is not
being explained here, but for some reason we have a little bit
of a stringency by eggs. Now you do have what I said
the what do you call it, we had been talking about sixty,
but remember that sixty was not in any משנה. רבא said oh
the rabbis say בשישים, beshishim, and the גמרא Gemara you know had
a whole line of teaching on on yesterday's דף. daf אמר רב
נחמן גיד בשישים, Amar Rav Nachman gid beshishim, this is בשישים, beshishim,
that's בשישים, beshishim, here בשישים ואחת, beshishim ve-achat, so ששים shishim clearly
was a dominant number that was emerging in the time of the
אמוראים, Amoraim, it was post-mishnaic, רש"י Rashi says this as well, there
was a transition moving from טעם to ששים. shishim. Okay, and we
see that there's some questions, fifty-nine, sixty-one, there was even the thirty
in some cases. So we're still going to hear for the rest
of today's דף work out the ששים shishim number. So let's take
a look. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל בר רבי. Hahu de-ata le-kammeih
de-Rabban Gamliel bar Rabbi. Somebody came to Rabban Gamliel the son of
Rabbi. So notice here by the way we're now in the door
of the תנאים, Tannaim, right, where where this is the first statement
I believe in the גמרא, Gemara right, that has actually ששים shishim
in the door of the תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, so somebody came in
front of Rabban Gamliel the son of Rabbi, אמר ליה, amar leih
but it's not a ברייתא Beraisa because it's all in Aramaic so
it's a tradition, אמר ליה amar leih said to him, so Rabban
Gamliel said to this questioner אבא לא שער בארבעין ושבע. Abba lo
shi'er be-arba'in ve-sheva. My father, you know, would not even use, you
know, would not wouldn't allow something with forty-seven times as much. מ"ה?
Mem-Heh? What? מ"ה? Mem-Heh? Forty-five?
Forty-seven. What are you talking about? ואני אשער בארבעין וחמש? Ve-ani asha'er
be-arba'in ve-chamesh? You want me to did I skip a line? No.
You want me to use forty-five? So meaning this guy was a
case where there was forty-five times the איסור and he brought the
question to Rabban Gamliel. Rabban Gamliel said my father had a case
with forty-seven he wouldn't allow it, so what do you want expect
me to allow it with forty-five? Okay, so it's but that's interesting
because it sounds like the exact number was still being sort of
figured out, right, he didn't just say oh no it's not
ששים. shishim. Now ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי שמעון בר רבי. Hahu de-ata
le-kammeih de-Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi. Now another case somebody came to Rabbi
Shimon the son of Rabbi and אמר ליה Amar lei, and he
said to the questioner אבא לא שער במ"ה, Abba lo shi'er be-mem-heh,
my father wouldn't even use forty-five, ואני אשער במ"ג? ve-ani asha'er be-mem-gimmel?
You want me to allow it with forty-three? So again it was
a case of forty-three and he says ha, my father wouldn't you
know was wasn't even allow a case with a bigger proportion, I
can't allow that. So again it seems like it's not like here
we have some statements from the תנאי Tannaic period that seems like
they're working to close to the sixty but they're not there yet,
there's still they what they know is even forty-five isn't going to
do it, even forty-seven isn't going to be good. What?
We got to wonder then why not sixty instead of sixty or
whatever.
Well okay they hadn't figured that out yet. They were working towards
it. Now רש"י Rashi by the way has a different way of
reading this which actually is is that he did permit it. If
you look at רש"י, Rashi, אבא, about fifteen lines from before they
get wide, הלא בא מעשה כזה לפניו, Halo ba ma'aseh ka-zeh le-fanav,
if my father had a case like this, ולא מצא אלא מ"ז
והתיר ve-lo matza ella mem-zayin ve-hi tayer and my father had forty-seven
and he permitted it, שמע מינה לאו ששים בעי, shma mina lav
shishim ba'ei, אף אני אתיר בזה. af ani atir be-zeh. I'll allow
it with forty-five. So the exact opposite. Not my father didn't allow
with forty-seven therefore I can't allow obviously with forty-five, but if my
father was going to be lenient with forty-seven, so I'll be lenient
also with forty-five, which is actually showing that they not only had
they not yet gotten up to sixty, but you know that they
were sort of had but they were actually ruling yet more leniently
than sixty at that stage. I don't exactly get how that would
work with the word because it says אבא לא שער, Abba lo
shi'er, meaning what, he did not measure it to make it forbidden
with forty-seven I guess is how you have to read that anyway
with forty-seven. Anyway according to one read they they forbade it but
they had not yet sort of crystallized sixty, according to the other
read they actually permitted it. permitted it with less than sixty.
But you've got to wonder why we even move to sixty?
Well, hold on. Okay, this was a process, you know, by the
time of the אמוראים, Amoroim, it had crystallized to sixty. Also notice
that sixty, by the way, was supposed to be a universal standard.
But if you imagine that it started by actually tasting it, then
we can't always taste it, can't always find a non-Jew, whatever. So
therefore, you know, especially if you need a non-Jewish chef, which was
a criterion that was set yesterday—debated how necessary that was. So you
can't always find it. Let's do a model. Let's figure out, let's
say it was like meat with turnips or, you know, they did
these models. Okay, so if you're doing models, so then it's possible
that based on what the איסור is, you might have a different
quantity that you're translating that number into. Sixty is a universal number.
Sixty is, don't bother yourself what the items were, what the forbidden
item was, what the היתר item was; take sixty that it'll—you'll always
be safe with sixty. So you can—you can understand how it took
time to get to there, right? You're going from taste, so you
might have numbers, but the numbers might fluctuate based on the cases.
And then you get a number of sixty, which is a firm
number that applies to all cases. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: הוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי חייא. Hu d'asal kamai d'Rabbi
Chiya. Somebody came to Rabbi Chiya. So again, we're dealing right at
the cusp of the Tanna—end of the Tannaitic period, the children of
Rabbi, Rabbi Chiya and so on. אמר ליה, he said to him:
כלום יש שלשים? Klum yesh shloshim? He says, hey, you know, there
isn't even thirty. Why are you asking me? Oh, that's interesting. טעמא
דליכא שלשים, Taama d'leika shloshim, the problem is that there isn't thirty.
הא איכא שלשים, Ha ika shloshim, if there is thirty, משרינן, mesharinan,
presumably according to Rabbi Chiya you can go by thirty. Is that
really true? I mean, all the numbers we've been saying now are
a lot more than thirty. So—oh well okay, so אמר רבי חנינא
גוזמא, Amar Rabbi Chanina guzma, he was exaggerating. What he means by
exaggerating, we're saying, what type of stupid question is it? There isn't
even thirty. Which doesn't mean that thirty would be enough, it's just,
why did you even ask the question? It's so obviously not good,
there isn't even thirty. All right. Now we're going to turn to,
until—although up until now I've been explaining this גמרא, the very sort
of, you know, the way it's really sort of very clearly emerges,
which is you start at the משניות Mishnayot with the idea of
taste, which is based on the biblical concept of taste. Then you
try to figure out how to determine taste, have a non-Jew taste
it, create models, then you finally get to using numbers and strict
numbers and sort of universal numbers of sixty. We're now going to
quote based on פסוקים, pesukim, ways that you can learn out the
number sixty and actually learn it from a פסוק. pasuk. And there's
a question here between רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosfos says
that's all אסמכתא. asmachta. Clearly sixty is a—is a number the rabbis
came up with as a stand-in for taste based on everything we've
seen, so don't take the whole דרשה drasha that we're coming to
discuss seriously. רש"י Rashi seems to say it is very serious. And
this I should say, by the way, is also sort of consistent
with the Ashkenazi approach, which actually said that numbers and the idea
of ששים shishim might really be a val—like a sort of a
measure in itself, not just a stand-in for taste, but there's a
real demand for, you know, for quantitative insignificance. And that's going to
be consistent with the next גמרא, which is going to downplay the
concern of taste and focus on the question of numbers. Okay, so
that's going to be like a shift from what we've seen until
now. Yes, question? This גמרא would seem to be very difficult for
the people who say that הלכה has never changed. Ah, well,
you'd have to ask what they exactly mean by that. But yes.
I mean, רש"י Rashi himself is explicit that, you know, the number
was not yet determined and so on. I mean, it clearly emerges
from the גמרא. All right. So let's take a look now, because
now—now we're going to shift to a place where it seems like
the numbers are the focus, not the idea of taste. So, אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא:
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar
Kappara: כל איסורין שבתורה בששים. Kol issurin sheba-Torah b'shishim. You measure all
forbidden things by ששים, shishim, which is what we said before. But
before we said because the rabbis under—actually no, I take that back.
Before we said you measure all things by the onion because rabbis
knew that nothing was, you know, no איסור whatever would have more
of a pungent taste than an onion, but we did start—we were
using sixty pretty much consistently through here. So this sort of distills
all of the previous גמרות Gemaras and says okay, now bottom line,
everything is sixty. Except the egg, which is sixty-one. Okay,
אמר לפניו רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק, amar l'fanav Rabbi Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak, רבי אתה אומר כן? Rabbi, ata omer kein? Do you
really say that? הכי אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
משום בר קפרא, Hachi amar Rabbi Assi, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
mishum Bar Kappara, there's another tradition in the name of בר קפרא,
Bar Kappara, because you're
say—because this—of רבי יהושע—this Rabbi Yehoshua is—this is רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי
בר קפרא; Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi bar Kappara; here's רבי אסי Rabbi
Assi in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי in the name
of בר קפרא. Bar Kappara. So the same first two stages, but
then it diverged at the third level of tradition. And here's another
tradition in the name of בר קפרא: Bar Kappara: כל איסורין שבתורה
במאה. Kol issurin sheba-Torah b'meah. Oh my God, you need a hundred
times as much! Okay, now that's actually a number that we know
from certain cases, certain rare cases, like תרומה terumah and ערלה, orlah,
there are some rare cases of agricultural things which are prohibited in
benefit that we need a hundred, but as a general rule, we—you
know, we never use the number hundred. A hundred, by the way,
I should say, is a number that does appear in משניות. Mishnayot.
Okay, and that appears in משניות Mishnayot in זרעים Zeraim by things
like תרומה terumah and ערלה, orlah, etc. So here somebody, this tradition
So says the גמרא, so that both of them, both of these
approaches although it's all from the name of בר קפרא, Bar Kappara,
but these two versions of בר קפרא Bar Kappara come from the
זרוע בשאילה, Zeroa b'Sheila, come from the arm of the ram of
מילואים, Miluim, the ram of שלמים Shelamim that is cooked for the
נזיר. Nazir. So it says you cook the arm of it goes
to the כהן Kohen and the arm of it is basically forbidden
for non-כהנים Kohanim to eat. It's
like קדשי קדשים. Kodshei Kodashim. And you cook it together with the
rest of the ram. So the question is how come the arm
doesn't impart its taste to the rest of the ram? How can
a non-כהן Kohen eat the rest of the ram? So that's going
to be a model for the quantities you need to negate when
two things are cooked together. דכתיב, Dechativ, the verse says: ולקח הכהן
את הזרוע בשאילה מן האיל. v'lakach ha-Kohen et hazroa b'sheila min ha-ayil.
The כהן Kohen shall take the cooked ram from the ram. The
arm basically is the forearm.
Okay? דתניא, Detanya, and we taught in a ברייתא: Braisa: בשאילה, B'sheila,
אין לי בשאילה אלא שלמה. ein li b'sheila ella shleima.
בשאילה B'sheila means whole. I'm not exactly clear how it means whole.
תוספות Tosafot says בשל לה, b'shel lah,
like it is with itself or something like that. Anyway, okay. Or
בשל לה, bashel lah, cook it, but cook it sort of whole,
I don't know. Anyway, אלא שלמה. ella shleima. רבי שמעון בן יוחי
אומר, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer, אין בשאילה אלא שנתבשלה עם האיל.
ein b'sheila ella shenitbashla im ha-ayil. No,
בשאילה b'sheila means that cooked everything is cooked together. It's not exactly
clear what they're disagreeing with. דכולי עלמא בהאי איל מבשלי. Dechulei alma
b'hai ayel mivashlei.
Everybody agrees that you cook the arm with the rest of the
ram. מר סבר מחתך לה והדר מבשלה. Mar savar mechatech lah v'hadar
mivashla.
First you cut it off and then you cook both of them
together. ומר סבר מבשלה והדר מחתך לה. U-mar savar mivashla v'hadar mechatech
lah. You cook it all together and then you separate them. They're
all being cooked in one big pot? Yeah, they're all being cooked
in the same pot, right? I guess it's a good question also
about how do you salt it to get out the salt, so
you must do that while the whole thing is whole. But you
don't have to sever the hand from the animal when you're cooking
it. And the other says no, you sever it and then you
cook them together. But either way it's going to be usable information
for us because you're cooking something forbidden to non-כהנים Kohanim with something
permissible in the same pot. It doesn't really matter much if they're
separated, if one has been cut off or not. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba-it
eima, if you want you could say דכולי עלמא מחתך לה והדר
מבשלה. dechulei alma mechatech lah v'hadar mivashla.
Everybody agrees you cut it off and then you cook it. מיהו
מר סבר בהדי איל מבשלה. Mihu mar savar bahadei ayil mivashla. One
holds you cook it together with the ram. ומר סבר בקדירה אחרת
מבשלה. U-mar savar b'kdeira achereta mivashla. You cook it separately. So somebody
says you actually cook it separately, right,
then that's not going to be relevant for our discussion because you're
not cooking it together with the rest of the ram. So ללישנא
קמא אליבא דדברי הכל, l'lishna kamma aliba de-divrei hakol, according to the
first approach our discussion works according to everybody because it doesn't matter
cut or not cut, it's cooked in the same pot. וללישנא בתרא,
V'lishna basra, according to the second approach, אליבא דרבי שמעון בן יוחי,
aliba de-Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, our discussion is according to רבי שמעון
בן יוחי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai because he would say that it's
being cooked in the same pot, where the one that says that
it means שלמה shleima means by itself, it's independent and in a
separate pot. Okay. That's all background. At the end of the day,
according to most approaches we have this arm being cooked with the
ram. Now the arm can't be eaten by non-כהנים, Kohanim, cooked with
the ram. How is it that the rest of it can be
eaten by non-כהנים? Kohanim? Aren't they, isn't it imparting its taste? Now,
so
let's take a look. מאן דאמר בששים, Man de-amar be-shishim, the one
that says that this is a model to tell you the idea
that you use sixty as a measure to say it's permissible, סבר
בשר ועצמות בהדי בשר ועצמות משערינן. savar basar v'atzamos bahadei basar v'atzamos
misha-arinan. You
the proportion of the arm to the rest of the body is
sixty, if you measure meat and bones against meat and bones. Okay?
As opposed to, והוי ליה בששים. v'havei lei be-shishim. That's a proportion
of one to sixty. Let's see what that contrasts to. מאן דאמר
במאה, Man de-amar be-meah, the one who says a hundred, מאן דאמר
במאה סבר בשר בהדי בשר משערינן. man de-amar be-meah savar basar bahadei
basar misha-arinan.
No,
you only look at meat, the proportion of the meat on the
arm to the meat of the rest of the body, not anybody
knows who's eaten a chicken when you get the arm, when you
get the פולקע, polke, right, there's not as much meat as when
you get other parts of the chicken because you've got a big
bone there. Okay?
So if you're doing the meat against the meat, the proportion is
going to be, there'll be more proportional meat in the rest of
the body than there is proportional meat on the arm part of
the body. You understand that, right? Think about the פולקע, polke, right?
There's less, it's about even the amount of bones to meat. In
the rest of the body there's more meat relative to bones. So
if you compare meat to meat, then there's going to be much
more meat, you know, the proportions are going to be much heavier
on the, you know, much more meat than if you're comparing the
whole, the bone with the meat to the bone with the meat.
So, one
minute, בשר בהדי בשר משערינן, basar bahadei basar misha-arinan, we compare meat
to meat, והוי ליה במאה. v'havei lei be-meah. And it's a hundred.
So everybody agrees from this is our basis to say that if
you've got these proportions you don't have to worry about the things
that it was cooked with. But what are the proportions? So רש"י
Rashi says, and this is also the question about similar to the
egg question, right, do you say bones absorb taste and do you
say bones give off taste? There's marrow in bones, right, do they
give off taste and do they absorb taste? Maybe even if they
do, maybe it's not the same degree that meat does, so what's
a fair way of determining the proportions here? By the way, you
know, I mean normally by the way we don't make those distinctions.
Remember the גמרא said before, how do you determine sixty? Oh, it's
everything in the pot, the gunk and the potatoes and even the
walls of the pot theoretically. So normally, you know, we and presumably
also though if you we didn't discuss let's say you have a
how much whether you count the bones of the טריפה treifa thing
and the marrow in the bones. So this is a question, what
type of things do you assume absorb, what type of things do
you assume give off? So therefore, the approach that says you treat
the whole thing, the bones are a problem but the bones will
also absorb, so the ratio of the arm to the rest of
the body is one to sixty. The one that says you only
look at meat, the meat giving off taste, the meat absorbing, says
the ratio of the meat on the arm to the meat of
the rest of the body is one to a hundred. This becomes
our model. Now notice here, no discussion of taste. Not only is
there no discussion of taste, there can't be a discussion of taste
because it all tastes the same. It's all meat. So here is
a concept of using numbers without any reference to a concern of
taste. So תוספות Tosafot, says this is all rabbinic because it doesn't
have taste. It's not a biblical problem here at all, so this
is all an אסמכתא asmachta and really the numbers are just a
stand-in for taste like we've been learning before. רש״י, Rashi, however, says
no. רש״י Rashi says it is a biblical demand that there be
a quantitatively greater amount of היתר regardless of taste issues and we
really are learning it from this. But that's again consistent with an
אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach, although the אשכנזים generally don't say רש״י, Rashi they
generally admit that the sixty is rabbinic and so on, but still
it's consistent with an approach to focus on the importance of the
number independent of taste. So a way to understand this by the
way of the significance of a quantitative amount independent of taste is
when רמב״ם Rambam describes why something is בטל batel and he uses
numbers like sixty or a hundred, he doesn't say because most of
the time you won't be able to taste it. The way the
רמב״ם Rambam phrases it is עד שיבטל הדבר מעוצם מיעוטו, ad she-yibatel
ha-davar me-otzem mi'uto, until something is nullified because of its, sort of
extreme smallness, there's got to be a better way of saying that,
because of its extreme minuteness. So therefore for רמב״ם, Rambam, part of
the reason that the way ביטול bitul works is not just by
negating taste but by something being quantitatively insignificant. So for that is
the focus on numbers independent of taste. So that's what רש״י Rashi
says. רש״י Rashi, actually goes further based on this גמרא to say
that we actually rule that taste is not a biblical concern. טעם
כעיקר Tam k'ikar is not דאורייתא. What? He says yeah, okay that's
either rabbinic or those are earlier אמוראים, Amoraim, but based on this
גמרא's emphasis of numbers and ignoring taste, רש״י Rashi says that taste
is not a biblical concern. One of these huge תוספות, Tosafot okay,
you know, this רבא אמר Rava amar or this big big תוספות
Tosafot whatever, basically, you know, spends a lot of energy completely rejecting
רש״י, Rashi but just to be aware that that's how far רש״י
Rashi goes by taking this גמרא seriously that emphasizes the numbers issue
and not the taste issue.
Yeah. So what I'm trying to understand is why can't we just
say for the first hook, גזירת הכתוב? gezeirat ha-katuv? Yeah. Well the
גמרא will get to that. And then second of all, I mean
how do you use this as a paradigm if אין מבטלין איסור
לכתחילה ein mevatlin issur le-chatchila anyway?
We'll get to that in a second too. How can רש״י Rashi
do that? The משנה says... Okay, it doesn't say if it's biblical,
it says taste of course is a concern. We're not denying it's
a concern, but רש״י says here we've got פסוקים, pesukim, we're talking
about a hundred and sixty, we're not talking about taste. So רש״י
actually says not only is the number also significant, independently significant, he
goes so far to even reject taste as biblical and then that's
going a little far. But certainly what you get from this גמרא
even though תוספות Tosafot insists on an אסמכתא asmachta is giving some
real weight to the issue of numbers in itself. Okay, so let's
keep on going. So the גמרא says like this,
and Michael's questions are right up, are coming right up now. You
should be very glad that תוספות Tosafot goes to town a lot
of places because it makes our דפים dapim shorter. Okay.
So the גמרא says: ומי ילפינן מינה? u-mi yalfinan minah? How can
you learn out from this case about the שלמים? shelamim? והתניא זהו
היתר הבא מכל איסור. ve-hatanya zehu heter ha-ba mi-kol issur.
This is a case, we have a ברייתא Baraita that comments on
this and says this is a case of something permissible that under
other circumstances would be forbidden. Okay, which means that זהו למעוטי מאי?
zehu le-ma'utei mai? What's that excluding? לאו למעוטי כל איסורין שבתורה? lav
le-ma'utei kol issurin she-ba-Torah? Is it not excluding other cases? You can't
learn out from here. But of course notice, you can't learn out
from here because we're saying this is too lenient. This is a
special leniency, okay, which maybe means that in other cases even that
wouldn't be enough. So anyway, but how do you learn out from
that? אמר אביי לא נצרכה אלא לרבי יהודה דאמר מין במינו לא
בטיל ומשום הכי הכא בטיל. Amar Abaye lo nitzrecha ela le-Rabbi Yehuda
de-amar min be-mino lo batel u-mishum hachi hacha batil. No,
no, no. What it means that this is a special leniency is
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. You might remember רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
from זבחים Zevachim and מנחות Menachos and actually we had it just
similarly before by כיסוי הדם, kissuy ha-dam, that if blood gets mixed
up with other blood, no matter how much the proportions are, it's
never בטל batel because if things are kind and the same kind
are mixed up, it's all blood, so it's never בטל. batel. Here
it was all meat, it's never בטל. batel. is רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi
Yehuda's position. You might remember רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. from זבחים Zvachim
and מנחות, Menachos, and actually we had it just similarly before by
כיסוי הדם, Kisoy Hadam, that if blood gets mixed up with other
blood, no matter how much the proportions are, it's never בטל, batel,
because if things are kind and the same kind are mixed up,
it's all blood, so it's never בטל. batel. יהודה Yehuda is all
meat, it's never בטל. batel. So when do we say this is
a special leniency? It's according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That ברייתא
Braisa was according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say if it's all the same, then it's never בטל, batel,
no matter what the proportions are. Now, here the Torah made a
special leniency, a special exception, 100 or 60 was מבטל mevatel it.
So it's only a special case according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that doesn't like even מין במינו. Okay, so קא משמע לן דהכא
בטיל, ka mashma lan de-hacha batil, here it is nullified. So the
Gemara says וליגמור מיניה, ve-ligmor minei, so why doesn't Rabbi Yehuda learn
from this that his principle is wrong, right? Why do you treat
this as an exception? Maybe this should tell you that even if
it's like and like, מין ומין, min u-min, it can be בטל.
batel. How does Rabbi Yehuda hold his position that normally ביטול bitul
does not work? So the Gemara says גלי רחמנא ולקח מדם הפר
ומדם השעיר, gali rachmana u-lakach mi-dam ha-par u-mi-dam ha-sair,
that it says this is where Rabbi Yehuda gets this idea from,
that you should take from the blood of the ox and the
blood of the goat by Yom Kippur. There you go, עניינא דיומא,
inyana de-yoma, and you mix it up and it says and then
you sprinkle it. שתרווייהו בהדי הדדי נינהו ולא בטילי, she-traveihu behadi hadadi
ninhu velo batili, they're mixed together and it's considered like you have
both bloods, even though he says clearly you have a lot more
blood from an ox than from a goat. So you see that
because they're both blood, it's never בטל. batel. So he has a
basis. Okay, the Gemara says, so now we have two sources. He
has this פסוק pasuk about blood to say like things are never
בטל. batel. But you have the case about the ram and the
arm, that's a case where it is בטל, batel, that you don't
worry about the taste that's given off by the arm. So which
does he determine is the rule and which does he determine is
the exception? ומאי חזית דגמירת מהאי, u-mai chazit de-gamirat me-hai, why do
you learn out from that one, from the one about blood? ליגמור
מהאי, ligmor me-hai, learn out from ours, from the ram and the
arm, that even when it's the same things, מין ומין, min u-min,
it is בטל. batel. חידוש הוא וחידוש לא גמרינן. chidush hu ve-chidush
lo gamrinan.
No, this case is a חידוש chidush and you can't learn anything
else from it. Now, why is it a חידוש? chidush? Of course,
we are learning something out, the Gemara gets at that. But what
is the חידוש? chidush? So here רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both
say the חידוש chidush is what Michael's question was, who said that
we let you לכתחילה lechatchila cook things together. Normally we say אין
מבטלין איסור לכתחילה, ein mevatlin issur lechatchila, you can't be מבטל, mevatel,
you know, something that, you can't throw חזיר chazir into the pot
and go oh I have 100 against it, I'll cook them together.
No, you're not allowed to do that to intentionally mix them. And
here we let you לכתחילה lechatchila cook it together. Now, it's not
exactly איסור here, it is an איל ayil that's eaten by a
כהן, kohen, but it's something that from your perspective as a non-כהן
kohen can't be eaten and we let you cook it together. Now
the problem with this is, is that according to a lot of
אחרונים, achronim, and not only that, according to a lot of ראשונים,
אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה ein mevatlin issur lechatchila is only a rabbinic
ruling, not a biblical ruling. So what would that mean here that
this is a חידוש chidush if it's not a חידוש chidush on
biblical terms? And they actually have a hard time with that trying
to figure out what the חידוש chidush is, because this Gemara, it's
hard to sort of point to a clear חידוש chidush other than
the fact that we're allowing you to cook it together. So that
would indicate that מבטלין איסור לכתחילה mevatlin issur lechatchila is a biblical
concern. Okay, but now that we've said, one minute, so we've said
now, okay, so this is a case where ביטול bitul worked, it
was an exception, we were lenient because Rabbi Yehuda normally doesn't allow
ביטול bitul by same types, but for him it's an exception and
ביטול was allowed. But that's not a general model because the Torah
is being lenient here anyway, it's letting you cook it together. Okay,
so this is a whole exception. Now that it's a whole exception,
how are we going to learn out from it the principle of
60 and 100? So let's just read that line and then I'll
take your question, Charlie. So the Gemara says אי הכי למאה וששים
נמי לא ליגמר. ei hachi le-me'ah ve-shishim nami lo ligmar. If that's
true that the whole case is an exception, how can we learn
out the principle of 100 or 60? So the Gemara says אטו,
atu, what do you think? אנן לקולא גמרינן? anan le-kula gamrinan? Are
we learning out from there to be lenient? To be lenient you
can't learn out from the case of the זרוע בשלה zroa beshela
because the whole case is lenient, we allow you to cook it
together to begin with. But we're not learning out a leniency from
this, לחומרא גמרינן, le-chumra gamrinan, we're learning out
a stringency, דמדאורייתא ברובא בטיל, de-mi-de'oraita be-ruba batil, biblically it would be
negated in רובא. ruba. Now why would it be negated in רובא?
ruba? So says רש"י, Rashi, because biblically we don't, taste is not
a concern biblically. That's what רש"י Rashi says here, because biblically the
whole concern about taste is only rabbinic, although there are opinions that
it's biblical, this Gemara is assuming that it's rabbinic and that's why
the only issue here is numbers and not taste. תוספות Tosafot says
wait, what are you talking about? The reason here you don't have
to worry about taste is because the whole thing tastes the same.
So even if you say that there's a biblical concern of טעם,
here the concern is not present, here it all tastes the same.
So to demand 60 or 100 from this is not a leniency,
it's a stringency because I would normally say if everything tastes the
same, just go by רוב. rov. I'm learning from the case of
the ram to say no, you need the same proportions as you
had by the ram, you need 60 or 100 even though it
all tastes the same, even though I should be able to go
by רוב. rov. So that's a stringency. Now you could say again,
take that and take that very literally and say okay that's even
biblical, that even if you don't have taste, that's one concern, טעם,
and that's addressed however you get addressed it, that you don't have
taste. From the ram we learn out that there's another biblical concern
about quantitative insignificance and about 60 and 100 independent of taste. But
תוספות Tosafot says, resists that, although it's clear like it's a פשט
pshat of the Gemara, תוספות Tosafot, resists saying there are two things
going on here, it says this whole thing is an אסמכתא asmachta
and at the end of the day the 60 is really just
a stand-in. for taste, it's not independent of the taste concern. Charlie,
you had a question?
Yeah, the issue of the cooking there is the foreleg for the
כהן Kohen with the rest of the שלמים. Shelamim. Yeah, isn't there
a general principle that Rabbinic prohibitions don't apply in the Temple?
Yeah,
much more about things like שבת, Shabbat, like אין שבות במקדש, Ein
Shvut B'Mikdash, because there we have to give you a lot of
latitude in order to bring the קרבנות Korbanot and so on.
In the first place, yeah, but you wouldn't bring a שלמים Shelamim
on שבת. Shabbat. What? You wouldn't bring a שלמים Shelamim on שבת.
Shabbat.
No, but
the principle is basically about Rabbinic שבת Shabbat restrictions don't apply. Ah,
okay. Not, I'm sorry, I did not mean Rabbinic restrictions don't apply
when it's שבת. Shabbat. Rabbinic restrictions related to שבת Shabbat don't apply.
In other types of areas, it's not so clear. I mean, there
might be some places, yes, but not certainly not as a blanket.
Yeah.
And in terms of things tasting the same, so this raises an
interesting question, because you know, if you asked me, I'd say it
doesn't all taste the same. White meat tastes very different than dark
meat.
Yeah, so that's דב Dov's question about how different it would have
to taste. So, yeah, if you take a look at the, I
mean, when this is brought down in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch,
the פרי מגדים Pri Megadim gives a whole long list of discussions
about like how different things taste to be considered a different taste.
I think white meat and dark meat are said that they are
close enough, but,
but yes, it is a question, but how different is, yeah.
So the animal would all be considered the same even though different
cuts, even if some is
softer, more tender, or more fat? That's right. That's pretty implicit here
in and of itself.
I doubt if you could tell the difference between chicken soup made
with dark meat and chicken soup made with white meat.
No, I'm saying,
but the soup, the soup does taste different. No, I'm saying, but
your eating,
the taste that it gives off, that's a good point.
But you never bring a chicken as a קרבן.
Korban. No, I know.
No, but what I was saying, the taste it gives off is
not necessarily the taste of what is inside, because some of that
taste is based on the texture. Right, that's a good point. Okay.
All right. So now that was one answer. Now we're going to
say,
remember, that was a question about that there was a line in
the ברייתא Braita we had to explain that says, oh, this is
exceptional, this is something מותר Muttar that's normally forbidden. What did that
mean? So the first explanation was according to רבי יהודה who normally
says
like things are never בטל, Batel, here it is בטל. Batel. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, לא נצרכה אלא טעם כעיקר, Lo nitzrecha ela tam
k'ikar, and this really is the line that supports Rashi. The whole,
this is telling you in terms of the principle that taste is
like the thing itself, דבקדשים אסור, De-be-kodashim assur, קמשמע לן דהכא שרי.
Kamashmalan de-hacha sharei. Normally by קדשים Kodashim it's forbidden. Here it's permissible.
So what do we mean that this is an exceptional case that
we're allowing something we normally don't allow? It means that we're now
only caring about sixty and a hundred and we're not caring about
the other concern of taste. So the fact that we only care
about sixty and a hundred, that makes this exceptional that we completely
ignore the concern of taste. Now that's funny because a couple things.
First of all, it all tastes the same, it's all מין במינו.
Number two is that maybe we're not ignoring the concern of taste,
maybe we're saying it's addressed by the sixty and a hundred.
So תוספות, Tosafot you know, really sort of struggles to explain that,
but Rashi emphasizes the idea that says טעם כעיקר Tam k'ikar is
a problem by קדשים, Kodashim, which suggests that by non-קדשים, Kodashim, by
non-קרבנות, Korbanot, טעם כעיקר Tam k'ikar. is not a problem. Okay, so
that's again where Rashi gets his idea that in this סוגיא we're
really assuming taste is not a problem in other places. But it
is a problem by קרבנות, Korbanot, here we're ignoring it, that's why
we're being lenient. Now תוספות Tosafot again says, what do you mean
we're ignoring it? It all tastes the same and anyway you have
sixty and a hundred. So תוספות Tosafot says, doesn't even really mean
טעם כעיקר. Tam k'ikar It really means when you have residual taste,
because the whole question by the way about taste is taste like
what? If I taste some, if I can tell that let's say
something was put in here, but it doesn't taste like the thing
itself, is that considered taste? How much taste? So תוספות Tosafot says
here the phrase of טעם כעיקר Tam k'ikar. which is only a
problem by קרבנות Korbanot does not mean normal טעם כעיקר. Tam k'ikar
Normal טעם כעיקר applies by everything. תוספות Tosafot, insists very clearly, טעם
is a biblical concern. What does this mean? It means here if
you already have sixty and a hundred and you have some tiny
little residual taste, that might normally be a problem by קרבנות, Korbanot,
here it is not a problem. And that's why this is an
exception that we are being lenient here. Let's just finish this point
up. וליגמר מינה, Veligmar minei, so why don't we learn from this
a general rule that that type of, I'll read like תוספות, Tosafot
residual taste is not a problem? Why do I normally assume that
even residual taste is a problem by קרבנות? Korbanot?
So גזר רחמנא גבי חטאת, Geder rachmana gabei chatat, no, because the
Torah tells you by a חטאת, Chatat, כל אשר יגע בבשרה יקדש,
Kol asher yigga b'vesarah yikdash, anything that touches the flesh of a
חטאת Chatat will be holy, which means the status of the חטאת
Chatat transfers to something that touched it and absorbed its taste. להיות
כמוהו, Lihyot kamohu, it becomes like it. שאם פסולה, She'im psulah, if
the חטאת Chatat was invalid, תפסל, Tipasel, the thing that absorbed from
the juices of the חטאת Chatat also is treated as invalid even
if it's a קרבן. Korban. ואם כשירה, Im kesherah, if the חטאת
Chatat was kosher, תאכל כחומר שבה, Tochol k'chomer she-bah, you have to
treat the animal that absorbed the juices of a חטאת Chatat like
the stringency of a חטאת. Chatat. A חטאת Chatat can only be
eaten for one day, so even if a two-day קרבן Korban touched
it and absorbed its juices, it too can only be eaten for
one day. So you see, now notice by the way, it's a
קרבן Korban presumably touching a חטאת, Chatat, so it's מין במינו, and
even so the transfer of juices is enough to say that it
is forbidden. So there you see that by קרבנות, Korbanot, even though
it's not real taste, even though it's same and same Even though
it may be only residual taste, it's normally a problem. So by
קרבנות Korbanot sometimes we have the problem even when it's not real
taste and here we're being lenient, this is the exception. So the
גמרא says ומה חזית דגמירת מהאי ליגמור מהאי, u'mah chazis d'gamiras me'hai
ligmar me'hai, why do you learn again from the case the rule
is the חטאת Chatas that residual taste is a problem, learn from
us that residual taste is not a problem? No, חידוש הוא ומחידוש
לא גמרינן, chiddush hu u'michiddush lo gamrinan, our case is a whole
חידוש chiddush cause we allow you to do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So
our case is a big leniency so we don't learn out leniencies
in our case to ignore residual taste. So the גמרא says אי
הכי דמאה וששים נמי לא ליגמר. ee hachi d'meah v'shishim nami lo
ligmar. So again, so therefore let's not learn out a hundred and
sixty if we're not going to learn out from our case. אטו
אנן לקולא גמרינן? Atu anan l'kula gamrinan? What do you mean? You
think we're being lenient based on a hundred and sixty? לחומרא קא
גמרינן, L'chumra ka gamrinan, we're being strict. דאורייתא ברובא בטיל, D'Oraisa b'ruva
bateil, again same as before. Without this learning of from איל בשילא
Ayil Bashila we would have said that biblically you go by majority.
Why? According to רש''י Rashi because there's no idea of טעם biblically,
according to the תוספות Tosafot and everybody else there is an idea
of טעם but it's all the same taste. So therefore you would
not have needed. And therefore this is telling us a stringency that
it's not enough to have רוב, rov, even when it all tastes
the same you need sixty or a hundred. And again תוספות Tosafot
says that's all דרבנן because that's really a stand-in, really when it's
the same מין במינו you really only do need רוב rov biblically.
But anyway תוספות Tosafot says it's all דרבנן. But again another way
of reading this is even if we admit to תוספות that taste
is not—is biblical and here it all tastes the same, maybe this
is teaching you that independent of taste there's another concern of quantity
and of proportions and of a hundred and sixty.